<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gndem.org/es/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://gndem.org/es/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-01T20:53:42+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/</id><title type="html">Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors</title><subtitle>The Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors connects over 245 regional networks and individual nonpartisan citizen observation groups to share best practices and further our common aspirations for representative, responsive, transparent, democratic governance.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">EMDS Finds Azerbaijan Elections in Violation of National Legislation and International Standards</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/emds-finds-azerbaijan-elections-in-violation-of-national-legislation-and-international-standards/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EMDS Finds Azerbaijan Elections in Violation of National Legislation and International Standards" /><published>2020-03-20T21:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-20T21:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/emds-finds-azerbaijan-elections-in-violation-of-national-legislation-and-international-standards</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/emds-finds-azerbaijan-elections-in-violation-of-national-legislation-and-international-standards/">&lt;p&gt;On February 9th, Azerbaijan held snap parliamentary elections with only two months’ notice - and nine months earlier than planned following a 99-1 vote to dissolve parliament in December 2019. The vote came after Prime Minister Novruz Mammadov unexpectedly resigned in October and was replaced by Ali Asadov, an ally of longtime President Ilham Aliyev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aliyev has remained in power since 2003, when he took over from his father. Referenda on presidential terms abolished term limits and extended terms to seven years. In 2017, Aliyev appointed his wife as his Vice President. International watchdog groups and citizen observers have regularly decried civil rights abuses during election periods including restrictions of freedom of assembly and expression, persecution of political opponents and activists, and voting irregularities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MPs hailed their December &lt;a href=&quot;https://eurasianet.org/azerbaijan-parliament-dissolves-setting-up-snap-elections&quot; title=&quot;decision&quot;&gt;decision&lt;/a&gt; to dissolve parliament as consistent with positive political reform, suggesting that that the snap elections would empower a younger generation of lawmakers to help “renew the Azerbaijani parliament’s activity so that it is consistent with the country’s dynamic development and comprehensive reform strategy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aliyev’s New Azerbaijan Party won all but one seat in a vote that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://smdtaz.org/en/&quot; title=&quot;Election Monitoring and Democracy Studies Center&quot;&gt;Election Monitoring and Democracy Studies Center&lt;/a&gt; (EMDS) concluded violated international standards for free and fair elections, due to the closed pre-election environment, interference from local authorities on election-day, and cases of violence against independent and opposition candidates and observers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EMDS based their conclusions - detailed in a February &lt;a href=&quot;https://smdtaz.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/EMDS-100220.pdf&quot; title=&quot;report&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; - on long term observation of the pre-election environment and a sample-based observation (SBO) on election day - no small feat given the snap nature of the elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EMDS found that the pre-election environment improved in several ways since the 2015 parliamentary elections, detailed in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://smdtaz.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/01/EMDS-Interim-Report-ENG-son.pdf&quot; title=&quot;first&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://smdtaz.org/en/emds-issued-the-second-interim-report-on-the-9-february-2020-early-parliamentary-elections-in-azerbaijan/&quot; title=&quot;second&quot;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; interim reports. Notably, there was more public interest in the campaigns and a higher number of independent and opposition candidates. However, there were no discussions or televised debates featuring candidates from outside the president’s party. While EMDS did not record violations during the nomination and registration of candidates, the organization noted pressure against nominees and interference of local officials in campaign processes. The campaign process was largely violence-free, though controlled by the ruling party. EMDS concluded that overall, an uncompetitive campaign process coupled with long-term embedded restrictions on information limited voters’ choice and restricted political freedoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On election day, the organization deployed observers to 150 randomly sampled polling stations to conduct a sample-based observation. Several observers reported that they were removed from, or were asked to leave their posts. Moreover, observers noted similar fraudulent activity as recorded in previous elections, including cases of multiple votes per person, bussing in voters, ballot-box stuffing, and unregistered voting. Some voters reported being unable to find their names in voter lists. In addition to direct reports from deployed observers, EMDS was able to capture some of these violations by monitoring the Central Election Commission’s (CEC) live video feeds in polling stations, which EMDS &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SMDT_EMDS/status/1233773074778087425&quot; title=&quot;shared&quot;&gt;shared&lt;/a&gt; on social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, EMDS reports showed significantly lower turnout than the official figure released by the Central Election Commission (CEC) on election day, suggesting the snap election was not the agent of change hailed by the government. EMDS also noted discrepancies within official turnout data reported by the CEC, in particular that turnout figures announced throughout election day for certain constituencies appeared to be inflated compared to the final count at the end of the day (as recorded on the official protocols).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;


  &lt;img sizes=&quot;(max-width: 320px) 320px,
        (max-width: 375px) 335px,
        (max-width: 480px) 440px,
        (max-width: 675px) 635px,
        800px&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_320/v1584979360/gndem/EMDS_discrepancies_in_voter_turnout_2_isv50m.jpg  320w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_335/v1584979360/gndem/EMDS_discrepancies_in_voter_turnout_2_isv50m.jpg  335w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_480/v1584979360/gndem/EMDS_discrepancies_in_voter_turnout_2_isv50m.jpg  480w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_635/v1584979360/gndem/EMDS_discrepancies_in_voter_turnout_2_isv50m.jpg  635w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v1584979360/gndem/EMDS_discrepancies_in_voter_turnout_2_isv50m.jpg  800w&quot; src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v2/v1584979360/gndem/EMDS_discrepancies_in_voter_turnout_2_isv50m.jpg &quot; title=&quot;EMDS- Discrepancy in voter turnout numbers on Election Day&quot; alt=&quot;EMDS- Discrepancy in voter turnout numbers on Election Day&quot; /&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;img-caption&quot;&gt;EMDS- Discrepancy in voter turnout numbers on Election Day &lt;span class=&quot;img-caption__source&quot;&gt;EMDS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the polls closed, observers reported serious violations during the vote-counting process. Most commonly, observers reported that the protocol did not accurately reflect results in over 50% of the polling stations sampled. In addition, observers in some stations were denied a copy of the protocol all together, and in close to 40% of stations, vote counting was carried out behind closed doors. EMDS also &lt;a href=&quot;https://smdtaz.org/en/emds-findings-on-suspicious-voter-turnout-results-on-9-february-early-parliamentary-elections/&quot; title=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;highlighted&lt;/a&gt; that the official CEC data showed a suspiciously similar vote share going to the winning candidates across polling stations in the same constituency along with above average turnout rates as illustrated below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;


  &lt;img sizes=&quot;(max-width: 320px) 320px,
        (max-width: 375px) 335px,
        (max-width: 480px) 440px,
        (max-width: 675px) 635px,
        800px&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_320/v1584980774/gndem/EMDS_suspicious_results_beap0m.jpg  320w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_335/v1584980774/gndem/EMDS_suspicious_results_beap0m.jpg  335w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_480/v1584980774/gndem/EMDS_suspicious_results_beap0m.jpg  480w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_635/v1584980774/gndem/EMDS_suspicious_results_beap0m.jpg  635w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v1584980774/gndem/EMDS_suspicious_results_beap0m.jpg  800w&quot; src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v2/v1584980774/gndem/EMDS_suspicious_results_beap0m.jpg &quot; title=&quot;EMDS- Suspicious results on official protocols&quot; alt=&quot;EMDS- Suspicious results on official protocols&quot; /&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;img-caption&quot;&gt;EMDS- Suspicious results on official protocols &lt;span class=&quot;img-caption__source&quot;&gt;EMDS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EMDS called on the government to ensure publicly-funded debates to guarantee citizens’ ability to make informed decisions and increase public interest in future elections. The organization also called on District Election Commissions and the CEC to investigate all reports of violations and hold officials accountable. Going forward, EMDS recommended implementing online registration of observers and reforming the electoral code following suggestions from domestic observers, OSCE/ ODIHR and the Venice Commission of the Council of Europe in order to improve democratic processes and grow trust in the state.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Eurasia" /><category term="Azerbaijan" /><category term="EMDS" /><summary type="html">On February 9th, Azerbaijan held snap parliamentary elections following a vote to dissolve parliament in December 2019. President Ilham Aliyev’s New Azerbaijan Party won a majority of seats in a vote that GNDEM member Election Monitoring and Democracy Studies Center (EMDS) concluded violated Azerbaijani law as well as international standards for free and fair elections.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/v1584979360/gndem/EMDS_discrepancies_in_voter_turnout_2_isv50m.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Members Meet in Brussels for the Seventh Annual Implementation Meeting of the DoGP</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/gndem-members-meet-in-brussels-for-the-seventh-annual-implementation-meeting-of-the-dogp/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Members Meet in Brussels for the Seventh Annual Implementation Meeting of the DoGP" /><published>2019-12-13T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-13T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-meet-in-brussels-for-the-seventh-annual-implementation-meeting-of-the-dogp</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-meet-in-brussels-for-the-seventh-annual-implementation-meeting-of-the-dogp/">&lt;p&gt;On November 5 and 6, 2019, representatives from GNDEM members convened in Brussels, Belgium for the Seventh Implementation Meeting of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gndem.org/declaration-of-global-principles/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Declaration of Global Principles for Nonpartisan Election Observation and Monitoring by Citizen Organizations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (DoGP). This year, the European Commission Director-General for International Cooperation and Development (DEVCO) co-hosted the meeting alongside GNDEM. All regional network members attended this year’s meeting, representing 13 countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year’s meeting focused on challenges observers face - including closing political space in some parts of the world, ways to improve credible observation, and tactics for building effective global advocacy and solidarity amongst GNDEM members. In the wake of the recent deaths of two election observers in Mozambique and Afghanistan, respectively, and increasing challenges to observation, participants discussed GNDEM’s approach for responding to threats directed at observers. The group recognized the importance of publishing solidarity statements and also brainstormed about complementary actions that could be taken to provide more concrete protections to observers operating in insecure political environments. The GNDEM Coordinating Committee also discussed possibilities for building a stronger global advocacy network, and invited &lt;a href=&quot;https://crisisaction.org/&quot;&gt;Crisis Action&lt;/a&gt; to share lessons learned and best practices from their experience in forming coalitions for advocacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this year’s meeting taking place in Brussels, participants had the opportunity to meet with representatives from the European External Action Service (EEAS), DEVCO, and Directorate-General for European Neighbourhood Policy and Enlargement Negotiations (DG NEAR). These meetings were a great opportunity to share GNDEM, members’ work, and the Declaration of Global Principles with a broader audience. GNDEM representatives found this a useful experience to build relationships and engage with international organizations active in the international election observation space that could provide future support to citizen observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;


  &lt;img sizes=&quot;(max-width: 320px) 320px,
        (max-width: 375px) 335px,
        (max-width: 480px) 440px,
        (max-width: 675px) 635px,
        800px&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_320/v1576268771/gndem/IMG-2538_gi0on3.jpg  320w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_335/v1576268771/gndem/IMG-2538_gi0on3.jpg  335w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_480/v1576268771/gndem/IMG-2538_gi0on3.jpg  480w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_635/v1576268771/gndem/IMG-2538_gi0on3.jpg  635w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v1576268771/gndem/IMG-2538_gi0on3.jpg  800w&quot; src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v2/v1576268771/gndem/IMG-2538_gi0on3.jpg &quot; title=&quot;Joe Keyrouz,&quot; alt=&quot;Joe Keyrouz,&quot; /&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;img-caption&quot;&gt;Joe Keyrouz, &lt;span class=&quot;img-caption__source&quot;&gt;GNDEM Coordinating Committees Chair, gives remarks at panel at the EU Parliament. To the right, MEP Nacho Sánchez Amor and Cristina Castagnoli from the EU Parliament.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close out the meeting, Patrick Costello from the EEAS, Thomas Millar from DEVCO, Pat Merloe from NDI, and Member of the European Parliament (MEP) Nacho Sánchez Amor of the EU Parliament presented on a panel at the European Parliament on the importance of citizen election observation in promoting electoral integrity. In his opening remarks, MEP Sánchez Amor remarked that the work of citizen election observers is crucial for establishing credibility of observation missions, as they are able to observe the process before and after election day. As Thomas Millar discussed, citizen observers have a strong understanding of pre-election environments and can respond quickly incidents when they arise. Thus, forming strong partnerships between domestic election observation groups and international observers can strengthen the credibility and integrity of election observation work around the world. Patrick Costello acknowledged that GNDEM is crucial to this development of strong partnerships between international and citizen election observers as the DoGP allows international institutions like the EU to distinguish the organizations that conduct credible observation. Additionally, Pat Merloe spoke to the fact that GNDEM is an ideal space for empowering citizen observers to advance methodologies and share resources to improve electoral integrity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="SADC ESN" /><category term="WAEON" /><category term="EPDE" /><category term="ENEMO" /><category term="ENAR" /><category term="E-HORN" /><category term="ANDE" /><category term="Acuerdo de Lima" /><category term="ANFREL" /><category term="Global" /><summary type="html">Representatives from GNDEM members around the world convened in Brussels on November 5-6, 2019 for the Seventh Implementation Meeting of the Declaration of Global Principles (DoGP).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/v1576268718/gndem/IMG-2479_gaxyfy.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM and ANFREL Condemn the Abduction and Murder of Afghan Election Observer</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/gndem-and-anfrel-condemn-the-abduction-and-murder-of-afghan-election-observer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM and ANFREL Condemn the Abduction and Murder of Afghan Election Observer" /><published>2019-10-23T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-23T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-and-anfrel-condemn-the-abduction-and-murder-of-afghan-election-observer</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-and-anfrel-condemn-the-abduction-and-murder-of-afghan-election-observer/">&lt;p&gt;The Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors (GNDEM) and the Asian Network for Free Elections (ANFREL) condemn the abduction and murder of Shaheed Ali Naqi. Reports indicate that the Taliban abducted Shaheed a few days after Afghanistan’s September 28 presidential election as he was completing observation efforts. He was later found murdered. Shaheed was a youth member of the Afghan Civil Society Forum Organization (ACSFo), a nonpartisan group that works for the inclusion of civil society in bringing stability, peace, reconstruction and development to Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACSFo and other Afghan nonpartisan groups mobilized over 7,000 citizen election observers across the country’s 34 provinces for the presidential election as part of citizens’ demonstrating their will for democratic government that respects people’s fundamental human rights. Shaheed’s murder along with other heinous attacks cannot diminish that will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GNDEM and ANFREL extend sympathies to Shaheed’s family and colleagues and joins calls for the perpetrators to be brought to justice. We urge the Afghan authorities to do everything in their power to protect those in their country who engage in elections and broader democratic processes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Global" /><category term="ANFREL" /><summary type="html">Statement by the Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors (GNDEM) and the Asian Network for Free Elections (ANFREL) on the abduction and murder of Afghan Election Observer Shaheed Ali Naqi</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://gndem.org/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Statement on the Fatal Shooting of Mozambique Local Election Observation Mission Head</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/statement-on-the-fatal-shooting-of-mozambique-local-election-observation-mission-head/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Statement on the Fatal Shooting of Mozambique Local Election Observation Mission Head" /><published>2019-10-11T19:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-11T19:10:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/statement-on-the-fatal-shooting-of-mozambique-local-election-observation-mission-head</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/statement-on-the-fatal-shooting-of-mozambique-local-election-observation-mission-head/">&lt;p&gt;October 2019- The African Elections Observers Network (AfEONet) which is comprised of citizen observer groups in the East and Horn of Africa (E-HORN), West Africa Election Observation Network (WAEON) and the Electoral Support Network of Southern Africa (ESN-SA) has learnt with sadness the death of the head of Mozambique’s local election observer mission, Anastacio Matavele, who was shot on Monday, 7 October 2019. Matavele was shot in Xai-Xai, the capital of the South Eastern Gaza Province. AfEONet condemns such an act, especially as Sala da Paz, a group that monitors election-related violence, has alleged that the three assailants are known members of the riot police unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incident discourages the critical role of non-partisan groups in observing elections. The preamble to the Global Network of Domestic Election Monitors’ (GNDEM) Declaration of Global Principles for Non-partisan Election Observation and Monitoring by Citizen Organizations provides that, “&lt;em&gt;Non-partisan election observation and monitoring by citizen organizations has emerged as one of the most tangible and significant dimensions of democratic development around the globe.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As further elaborated in the preamble, “&lt;em&gt;Non-partisan observation and monitoring of elections by citizen organizations is part of participating in public affairs, which “relates to legislative, executive and administrative powers&lt;/em&gt;” and “&lt;em&gt;covers all aspects of public administration, and the formulation and implementation of policy….” (UNHRC General Comment 25, paragraph 5.) Non-partisan election observation and monitoring by citizen organizations exercises the right of association that is central to the functioning of nongovernmental organizations, as well as the right to seek, receive and impart information that is vital to transparency and is included in the freedom of expression protected by articles 19 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights and the ICCPR.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfEONet strongly condemns this act as election observers play a vital role in electoral processes. Chapter 5 of the African Charter on Democracy Elections, and Governance, on the culture of democracy and peace, particularly Article 4, 3 obliges States to “&lt;em&gt;Create conducive conditions for civil society organizations to exist and operate within the law.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stand in solidarity with the Civil Society Learning Center (CESC) and the NGO League in Mozambique (JOINT) in this very difficult time. Further, we call upon the government of Mozambique to ensure that the electoral environment is peaceful and that election observers are safe to carry out their mandate. We implore the State to investigate and ensure and the perpetrators are brought to book and justice served.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the full statement &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1efJimdF0H68_c4JP3Nxi2BR4fzNEnTu1/view?usp=sharing&quot; title=&quot;Statement on the Fatal Shooting of Mozambique Local Election Observation Mission Head&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="E-HORN" /><category term="WAEON" /><summary type="html">Statement by the African Elections Observers Network (AfEONet), compromised of citizen observer groups in E-HORN, WAEON, and ESN-SA, on the fatal shooting of local election observation mission head in Mozambique</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://gndem.org/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Members Convene in Belgrade to Discuss Disinformation in Elections</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/gndem-members-convene-in-belgrade-to-discuss-disinformation-in-elections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Members Convene in Belgrade to Discuss Disinformation in Elections" /><published>2019-09-30T21:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-09-30T21:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-convene-in-belgrade-to-discuss-disinformation-in-elections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-convene-in-belgrade-to-discuss-disinformation-in-elections/">&lt;p&gt;In recent years digital disinformation has become a significant threat to the integrity of electoral processes and election environments. The spreading of false information inhibits voters from receiving impartial information, damages political reputations, discourages participation in elections, and encourages harassment or violence. By better understanding the tools available to them, election observers can more effectively expose and counter the election-related disinformation being spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representatives from several GNDEM member organizations attended an Academy on the impact of social media and elections in Belgrade, Serbia from 2-5 September 2019. This intensive academy, hosted by the National Democratic Institute (NDI), addressed the tools and strategies election observers can utilize for detecting, exposing, and countering malign disinformation in election environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Academy’s participants came from citizen election observation groups around the world including GNDEM members &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pacemyanmar.org/&quot;&gt;People’s Alliance for Credible Elections&lt;/a&gt; (PACE, Myanmar), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paffrel.com/&quot;&gt;People’s Action for Free and Fair Elections&lt;/a&gt; (PAFFREL, Sri Lanka), &lt;a href=&quot;https://pciudadana.org/&quot;&gt;Participación Ciudadana&lt;/a&gt; (PC, Dominican Republic), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.participacionciudadana.org/&quot;&gt;Corporación Participación Ciudadana Ecuador &lt;/a&gt;(PC, Ecuador), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdtmn.org/&quot;&gt;Center for Democratic Transition&lt;/a&gt; (CDT, Montenegro), &lt;a href=&quot;http://cemi.org.me/en/&quot;&gt;Center for Monitoring and Researching&lt;/a&gt; (CEMI, Montenegro), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oporaua.org/en&quot;&gt;Civil Network OPORA&lt;/a&gt; (Ukraine), &lt;a href=&quot;http://podlupom.org/v2/&quot;&gt;Coalition for Free and Fair Elections- Pod Lupom &lt;/a&gt;(Bosnia), &lt;a href=&quot;http://most.org.mk/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Citizen Association MOST&lt;/a&gt; (North Macedonia), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/&quot;&gt;International Society for Free Elections and Democracy&lt;/a&gt; (ISFED, Georgia), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://crta.rs/en/&quot;&gt;Center for Research Transparency and Accountability&lt;/a&gt; (CRTA, Serbia).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;


  &lt;img sizes=&quot;(max-width: 320px) 320px,
        (max-width: 375px) 335px,
        (max-width: 480px) 440px,
        (max-width: 675px) 635px,
        800px&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_320/v1569874064/gndem/20190904-152314_o52evr.jpg  320w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_335/v1569874064/gndem/20190904-152314_o52evr.jpg  335w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_480/v1569874064/gndem/20190904-152314_o52evr.jpg  480w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_635/v1569874064/gndem/20190904-152314_o52evr.jpg  635w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v1569874064/gndem/20190904-152314_o52evr.jpg  800w&quot; src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v2/v1569874064/gndem/20190904-152314_o52evr.jpg &quot; title=&quot;Participants discuss their exercise.&quot; alt=&quot;Participants discuss their exercise.&quot; /&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;img-caption&quot;&gt;Participants discuss their exercise. &lt;span class=&quot;img-caption__source&quot;&gt;NDI&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the four days, participants learned the steps and resources available for structuring and employing a social media monitoring effort. Participants began by assessing the information environments in their countries, thinking through where voters receive their information, popularity of media platforms, what types and themes of disinformation are most prevalent, and any existing efforts to combat disinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several participants, including representatives from GNDEM members, had the opportunity to present methodologies their organization have used in monitoring disinformation within their countries, demonstrating to peers how monitoring tools can work in specific situations. GNDEM member OPORA shared their research in the recent Ukrainian elections, where they used the Facebook Ad Library and API to identify prominent trends in political advertisements around the 2019 presidential and parliamentary elections. Using the Facebook Ad Library and API OPORA also conducted analysis regarding how ads were targeted by geography and demographics, the amount of money spent on ads and to what extent these amounts were formerly disclosed, and other coordination and transparency concerns related to online political finance. ISFED, GNDEM member from Georgia, presented another tool – Fact-a-lyzer, which analyzes data from Twitter and Facebook. During the 2018 Presidential elections ISFED monitored the Facebook accounts of various politicians and political parties for electoral activity violations, attempts to discredit candidates and processes, and divisive content. Fact-a-lyzer enabled the team to sort through thousands of posts and categorize them into groups to gain a clearer image the type of messages spread during the election. Participants also heard about Graphika and the use of big data through case studies presented by citizen observers and elections experts. Following the presentations, the participants had a chance to explore these tools for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To close out the academy, participants reviewed different methods and techniques to counter disinformation threats. They explored methods for advocating for a more open internet and fact-based political discourse. Additionally, they looked at ways to keep institutions accountable, to build an advocacy network, and to create effective messaging online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NDI also made available the resources used during the Academy that GNDEM members can use to direct their own strategy for mitigating disinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ndi.org/publications/disinformation-and-electoral-integrity-guidance-document-ndi-elections-programs&quot;&gt;A Guidance Document on Disinformation and Electoral Integrity &lt;/a&gt;(ENG)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IXsDGvL_nRc&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;Tactics, Trends, and Responses to Disinformation and Elections&lt;/a&gt; (ENG)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Global" /><summary type="html">Representatives from several GNDEM member organizations attended an Academy on the impact of social media and elections in Belgrade, Serbia from 2-5 September 2019. This intensive academy, hosted by the National Democratic Institute (NDI), addressed the tools and strategies election observers can utilize for detecting, exposing, and countering malign disinformation in election environments.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/v1569871936/gndem/IMG-1570_mmmdam.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Members Participate in Open Election Data Academy</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/gndem-members-participate-in-open-election-data-academy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Members Participate in Open Election Data Academy" /><published>2019-05-31T19:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-31T19:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-participate-in-open-election-data-academy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-participate-in-open-election-data-academy/">&lt;p&gt;As demand for open government data increases globally, many election management bodies (EMBs) around the world are making more electoral data public in a variety of ways. As a result, citizen election observers need to be equipped to advocate for, and analyze official election data. From March 31 to April 3, 2019, representatives from citizen election observer groups from around the world, including several GNDEM member organizations, gathered in Bogota, Colombia to participate in an Open Election Data Academy conducted by the National Democratic Institute (NDI). Participants came from every continent, representing 17 organizations including 15 GNDEM members. The academy drew on NDI’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openelectiondata.net/en/&quot;&gt;Open Election Data Initiative&lt;/a&gt;’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openelectiondata.net/en/academy/&quot;&gt;Election Data Academy&lt;/a&gt;, which is available to read and explore in English, Spanish, French, Arabic, Russian, and Burmese through practical modules on summarizing and analyzing election data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GNDEM members who participated in the academy included, among others: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bersih.org/&quot;&gt;BERSIH 2.0&lt;/a&gt; (Malaysia), &lt;a href=&quot;https://crta.rs/en/&quot;&gt;Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability&lt;/a&gt; (CRTA, Serbia), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isd.org.sv&quot;&gt;Iniciativa Social para la Democracia&lt;/a&gt; (ISD, El Salvador), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/eng&quot;&gt;International Society for Fair Elections and Democracy&lt;/a&gt; (ISFED, Georgia), &lt;a href=&quot;https://moe.org.co/&quot;&gt;Misión de Observación Electoral&lt;/a&gt; (MOE, Colombia), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.participacionciudadana.org/&quot;&gt;Participación Ciudadana&lt;/a&gt; (PC, Ecuador), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pciudadana.com/&quot;&gt;Participación Ciudadana&lt;/a&gt; (PC, Dominican Republic), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yiaga.org/&quot;&gt;YIAGA Africa&lt;/a&gt; (Nigeria), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zesn.org.zw/&quot;&gt;Zimbabwe Election Support Network&lt;/a&gt; (ZESN, Zimbabwe), and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://anfrel.org/&quot;&gt;Asian Network for Free Elections&lt;/a&gt; (ANFREL).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the intensive four-day academy participants explored innovative practices for gathering and analyzing official election-related data on key aspects of electoral integrity, as well as best practices for communicating and visualizing findings and advocating for more open election data. Participants also discussed how to assess their country’s election data context. Working with official data, academy participants learned about tools that are available to convert data from non-machine readable formats into open formats and tools that can extract data from websites into analyzable files. Through hands-on exercises, participants learned and practiced using Excel formulas to clean, summarize, describe and analyze data. They also learned how to look for patterns in data and practiced how to present and visualize data-driven findings to convey the right messages to their target audiences. Participants shared their organizations’ experiences and highlighted lessons learned from working with and advocating for election data. For example, YIAGA Africa and Misión de Observación Electoral (MOE) demonstrated how they have gathered and analyzed official data to identify early warning signs of potential electoral violence prior to elections in Colombia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;


  &lt;img sizes=&quot;(max-width: 320px) 320px,
        (max-width: 375px) 335px,
        (max-width: 480px) 440px,
        (max-width: 675px) 635px,
        800px&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_320/v1559327325/gndem/DSC03089.jpg  320w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_335/v1559327325/gndem/DSC03089.jpg  335w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_480/v1559327325/gndem/DSC03089.jpg  480w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_635/v1559327325/gndem/DSC03089.jpg  635w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v1559327325/gndem/DSC03089.jpg  800w&quot; src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v2/v1559327325/gndem/DSC03089.jpg &quot; title=&quot;Participants analyze data&quot; alt=&quot;Participants analyze data&quot; /&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;img-caption&quot;&gt;Participants analyze data &lt;span class=&quot;img-caption__source&quot;&gt;Participants analyze data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Academy participants also learned how disinformation affects electoral integrity by undermining democratic principles and citizens’ trust in elections, as well as how open election data can be a powerful tool to counter disinformation. For example, transparent and accessible data can help election management bodies combat rumors and increase citizen observers’ ability to fact-check information and inform citizens. During the academy’s disinformation sessions, ISFED shared how they monitored social media to assess the information environment around the Georgian elections, which helped expose coordinated efforts to spread disinformation about specific candidates. Participants discussed the challenges they face with disinformation in their countries and learned about strategies and methods to monitor disinformation in their own contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NDI has made the livestreams of three sessions from the academy available to watch online. These provide an opportunity for GNDEM members to learn about emerging trends in citizen election observation and how they are relevant for your organization. Find the links to the videos available in English and Spanish below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overview of Open Election Data: Why it Matters and How it Can be Used
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?reload=9&amp;amp;v=PQnI8i3SDpY&quot;&gt;English link&lt;/a&gt; (starts at 1:46:00)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=X-lRfYANYeo&quot;&gt;Enlace en español&lt;/a&gt; (empieza en 1:06:00)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Advocacy for Open Election Data: Getting and Asking for More Election Data
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EV5XaAnVNzM&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;English link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oj7g4U4-0PY&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;Enlace en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disinformation in Elections: How the Information Space Impacts Electoral Integrity
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wplsNNgjaDs&quot;&gt;English link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lscRqACP0ps&quot;&gt;Enlace en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Global" /><summary type="html">From March 31 to April 3, 2019, representatives from citizen election observer groups from around the world, including several GNDEM member organizations, gathered in Bogota, Colombia to participate in an Open Election Data Academy conducted by the National Democratic Institute (NDI).</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/v1559326604/gndem/DSC03000.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Implements New Membership Requirements</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/gndem-implements-new-membership-requirements/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Implements New Membership Requirements" /><published>2019-03-06T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-03-06T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-implements-new-membership-requirements</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-implements-new-membership-requirements/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;coordinating-committee-adopts-constitutional-protocols&quot;&gt;Coordinating Committee Adopts Constitutional Protocols&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-participates-in-two-events-in-colombo-sri-lanka/&quot;&gt;Sixth Implementation Meeting&lt;/a&gt; of the Declaration of Global Principles, held in 2018 in Colombo, Sri Lanka, the Coordinating Committee adopted the first set of &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=1a9jsUBSnI5jUtqBrNUKqMZedOkajr-pD&quot;&gt;GNDEM Constitutional Protocols&lt;/a&gt;, implementing new membership categories and criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the new protocols, current and prospective GNDEM members must conduct activities around the electoral cycle on a regular basis, have monitored at least one election in the past 10 years and have published a report from their observation, have endorsed the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gndem.org/declaration-of-global-principles/&quot;&gt;Declaration of Global Principles&lt;/a&gt; (DoGP), and submit a financial report at least every four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New membership categories will also be established based on the criteria above: “full members” includes groups that have been accredited for three consecutive years; “associate members” includes groups that haven’t fulfilled the requirement of accreditation for three consecutive years; and “consultative members” are those who don’t meet the membership criteria but wish to contribute to GNDEM and are endorsers of the DoGP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;accreditation-committee-releases-survey&quot;&gt;Accreditation Committee Releases Survey&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following GNDEM’s adoption of the Protocols, &lt;a href=&quot;https://moe.org.co/&quot;&gt;MOE Colombia&lt;/a&gt; - as the Chair of the Accreditation Committee - set out to build a comprehensive record of member organizations with the ultimate objective to establish a standardized accreditation process. MOE is currently surveying all current members, allowing the Accreditation Committee and GNDEM to know more about the organizations that are current members, understand their needs and capabilities, build a baseline for further comparison, and establish parameters from which to assess future applications from organizations seeking to be a part of the network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This survey is being conducted by MOE through 2 questionnaires. The questions included were formulated in line with the requirements established by GNDEM’s Constitutional Protocols to be a member of the network. These questionnaires were sent out to all organizations that are currently listed as GNDEM member organizations. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/forms/Ja4KjgxzMMNzILhr1&quot;&gt;first questionnaire&lt;/a&gt; was sent out within the period from November to December 2018. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/forms/AKoj6f8lZxjCsuTH3&quot;&gt;second questionnaire&lt;/a&gt; was recently sent out to the same GNDEM members to be completed by the end of February 2019. Once the data collection process is complete, MOE Colombia and GNDEM will consolidate and report the general information gathered through these questionnaires to inform the process for the formulation of a standardized accreditation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information or questions, or for a full copy of the GNDEM Constitutional Protocols, please email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:gndem09@gmail.com&quot;&gt;gndem09@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Misión de Observación Electoral" /><category term="Global" /><summary type="html">During the Sixth Implementation Meeting of the Declaration of Global Principles, the Coordinating Committee adopted the first set of GNDEM Constitutional Protocols, implementing new membership categories and criteria.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://gndem.org/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">ISFED Monitors Social Media Around 2018 Presidential Election</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/isfed-monitors-social-media-around-2018-presidential-election/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ISFED Monitors Social Media Around 2018 Presidential Election" /><published>2018-12-27T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-12-27T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/isfed-monitors-social-media-around-2018-presidential-election</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/isfed-monitors-social-media-around-2018-presidential-election/">&lt;p&gt;For the October 28, 2018 presidential election in Georgia, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/main/home/eng/&quot;&gt;International Society for Fair Elections and Democracy&lt;/a&gt; (ISFED) conducted a parallel vote tabulation (PVT) and general pre-election observation, monitoring abuse of administrative resources, incidents of intimidation and harassment, and the preparation of electoral administration. The PVT played an important role in assessing the integrity of election day processes and helped to verify &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/news/1/eng/3/&quot;&gt;official election results&lt;/a&gt;, showing the need for a runoff between the top two candidates, and the long-term observation allowed ISFED to identify problems and issue recommendations for improvement prior to election day. However, given emerging issues and concerns, ISFED also used the 2018 election to pilot a new initiative - monitoring social media during the pre-election period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISFED’s social media monitoring effort used a new tool called Fact-a-lyzer that was created especially for citizen election monitoring groups. The software works to ingest, aggregate, and monitor the content of posts on public Facebook pages for parties, candidates, local governments, and civil servants. Using the tool, ISFED’s set of social media monitors assigned tags to the content, such as ‘anti-immigration’ or ‘sponsored’, which, in turn, allowed ISFED to identify and analyze trends in content as published in their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/main/1429/eng/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isfed.ge/main/1465/eng/&quot;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt; reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the official pages of candidates and parties, ISFED tracked pages devoted to discrediting candidates and parties as well as narrative pages that promoted certain viewpoints. These pages contained a higher amount of sponsored posts than official pages, however the spending on sponsored content was not officially declared as a contribution to any campaign. According to Georgian law, these are illegal donations and such a pattern is signaling that the funds may have been coming from dubious sources. As they monitored Facebook pages, ISFED also uncovered attacks on civil society and NGOs. ISFED also took a closer look at the behavior of the different pages discrediting candidates and the electoral process. The data showed that posts shared on these anonymous pages were similar in content and formatting, suggesting an organized effort. This monitoring of the election campaign showed that social media was integral to spreading false and damaging information and could be used as a tool for circumventing legal restrictions on political financing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;&quot;&gt;


  &lt;img sizes=&quot;(max-width: 320px) 320px,
        (max-width: 375px) 335px,
        (max-width: 480px) 440px,
        (max-width: 675px) 635px,
        800px&quot; srcset=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_320/v1545858238/gndem/OUT%20OF%20160%20DISCREITING%20PAGES%20STUDIED.png  320w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_335/v1545858238/gndem/OUT%20OF%20160%20DISCREITING%20PAGES%20STUDIED.png  335w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_480/v1545858238/gndem/OUT%20OF%20160%20DISCREITING%20PAGES%20STUDIED.png  480w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,q_70,w_635/v1545858238/gndem/OUT%20OF%20160%20DISCREITING%20PAGES%20STUDIED.png  635w,
          https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v1545858238/gndem/OUT%20OF%20160%20DISCREITING%20PAGES%20STUDIED.png  800w&quot; src=&quot;https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/f_auto,w_800/v2/v1545858238/gndem/OUT%20OF%20160%20DISCREITING%20PAGES%20STUDIED.png &quot; title=&quot;ISFED Analysis of Discrediting Pages&quot; alt=&quot;ISFED Analysis of Discrediting Pages&quot; /&gt;

  
    &lt;figcaption class=&quot;img-caption&quot;&gt;ISFED Analysis of Discrediting Pages &lt;span class=&quot;img-caption__source&quot;&gt;ISFED&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISFED’s social media monitoring initiative proved to be very timely during the presidential election. Negative campaigning and harsh rhetoric were distinct features of the electoral campaign in Georgia, reaching its peak ahead of the runoff election. Facebook was a key vehicle used to wage smear campaigns, contributing to high polarization. ISFED found that discrediting Facebook pages targeting the two presidential candidates tripled in number ahead of the presidential runoff on November 28, 2018. Tactics used between the first and second rounds also included deceptive methods, such as the use of false media agency pages posing as media outlets and fake supporting pages created to discredit the very candidates they pretended to be supporting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ISFED intends to conduct further research and analysis on the data collected from the social media monitoring and to develop recommendations on how best to address the negative challenges that social media brings to the electoral process. ISFED also intends to analyze lessons learned and share experiences with other citizen observer groups through developing guidelines on social media monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="ISFED" /><summary type="html">Given emerging issues and concerns in Georgia, ISFED used the 2018 presidential election to pilot a new initiative - monitoring social media during the pre-election period.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/v1545857923/gndem/NUMBER%20OF%20PAGES%20DISCREDITING%20PRESIDENTIAL%20CANDIDATES.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Participates in Two Events in Colombo, Sri Lanka</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/gndem-participates-in-two-events-in-colombo-sri-lanka/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Participates in Two Events in Colombo, Sri Lanka" /><published>2018-11-19T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-19T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-participates-in-two-events-in-colombo-sri-lanka</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-participates-in-two-events-in-colombo-sri-lanka/">&lt;h3 id=&quot;coordinating-committee-convenes-in-colombo&quot;&gt;Coordinating Committee Convenes in Colombo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From August 25 to 26, 2018, the GNDEM Coordinating Committee, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gndem.org/members/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;representing the nine regional networks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, met in Colombo, Sri Lanka for the Sixth Implementation Meeting of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gndem.org/declaration-of-global-principles/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Declaration of Global Principles for Nonpartisan Election Observation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The Coordinating Committee discussed recent challenges and opportunities in citizen election observation, and further clarified and refined network priorities and standard operating procedures, including the approval of the first set of GNDEM Protocols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a meeting of the GNDEM Board, Coordinating Committee members participated in discussions and panels on topics relevant to GNDEM and election observation more broadly, including examples from their own organizations’ recent work in various thematic areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A panel on inter-election activity followed which featured presentations by representatives from Acuerdo de Lima, ENEMO, and E-HORN. A representative from Acuerdo de Lima discussed the deteriorating communication environment in Latin America and how it has led to significant problems for the region including fake news, online manipulation, and hate speech. She discussed how &lt;a href=&quot;https://moe.org.co/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misión de Observación Electoral (MoE)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a GNDEM member from Colombia, has been monitoring hate speech on social media and has been working to understand how stories evolve through social media and how people receive their information. A representative from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.enemo.eu/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENEMO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; followed with a presentation on the lack of trust in electoral institutions in Montenegro, and how domestic and regional monitoring organizations like ENEMO and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cemi.org.me/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Centre for Monitoring and Research (CeMI)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are promoting transparency in electoral results. He also discussed their efforts to work with the EU to push for electoral reforms. A representative from E-HORN highlighted the role citizen observers can play in electoral justice. She discussed many of the topics observer organizations in Kenya engage in between elections, such as reforms to the constitution, the observation and preservation of human rights, and the right to access of information. Keeping election monitoring organizations relevant and sustainable during non-election years was a common concern among participants, some of whom encouraged GNDEM to prioritize taking more concrete steps in response to these common and growing challenges in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group moved on to discuss a number of longer-term and pre-election initiatives to better meet emerging threats to democracy, including how to track, analyze, and combat disinformation in the electoral process, and how to plan for and implement an open election data advocacy, collection, and assessment effort. Participants from NDI and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epde.org/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPDE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; highlighted how open election data can be used to identify electoral manipulations, as well as the timing and feasibility considerations for obtaining and analyzing election data. The members identified possible sources for open data other than election management bodies (EMBs), including parliaments, statistics bureaus, and interior ministries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of disinformation to influence the electoral information environment was discussed in detail, as well as the growing prevalence of “zombie observers” and GONGOs undermining legitimate election observation. This was of particular concern to participants from European monitoring organizations. Participants discussed how to identify false citizen and international observation groups, and stressed the importance of monitoring the pre-election environment, and in particular, how groups could monitor disinformation or collaborate with other groups to include such analysis in their findings in order to build accountability around the threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group also discussed the potential for a GNDEM Election Observation Handbook to consolidate and present best practices among GNDEM member observer groups. They focused on the structure of the handbook and possible additions such as success stories, lessons learned, and infographics. The possibility of translations for such a handbook was also mentioned with several groups offering their own capacities and experience with this task. There was general consensus in regards to the purpose and overall intent of such a resource, as well as agreement to move forward in finalizing the structure and at least broad content over the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual meeting also offered the opportunity for GNDEM representatives to reflect on the medium and long-term objectives of the network, and strengthen structural and organizational practices to meet the growing challenges of the citizen election observation community. The Coordinating Committee approved the first set of GNDEM Constitutional Protocols, which codify GNDEM’s membership and accreditation requirements as well as leadership and internal working group structures (to be distributed widely in the coming months). The Coordinating Committee also held elections for board positions, with Joe Keyrouz (ANDE, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lade.org.lb/Home.aspx&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LADE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) remaining in his position as Chair for the next two years and Carol Werunga (E-HORN, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khrc.or.ke/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KHRC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) remaining in her position as Deputy Chair for the next three years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group discussed a plan to clarify and streamline the role of the Solidarity Working Group, including the process for issuing GNDEM solidarity statements in response to observer groups facing pressure or backlash from outside entities. They discussed the internal process of endorsement of statements as well as points of contact for statements and the review procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group closed the final day by discussing the establishment of GNDEM awards, with proposed awards recognizing groups making significant contributions to observation methodology or democratic advancement. The proposal for such an award was adopted by the committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gndem-participation-in-asian-electoral-stakeholder-forum&quot;&gt;GNDEM Participation in Asian Electoral Stakeholder Forum&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Implementation Meeting, GNDEM members took part in the Fourth &lt;a href=&quot;https://anfrel.org/aesf-iv/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asian Electoral Stakeholder Forum (AESF IV)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, hosted by ANFREL, from August 27 to 28. After an opening keynote address by H.E. Maithripala Sirisena, the President of Sri Lanka, three plenary sessions were held. The first session featured updates from countries that have seen significant changes in electoral integrity. The second focused on trends of shrinking democratic space and emerging regional challenges. Highlights of the session included discussions on disinformation, best practices for the participation of minority groups and indigenous peoples, the progress towards achieving gender parity in elections, and access for people with disabilities. The last panel focused on how to foster credible electoral processes, including the role of civil society groups as agents of credible elections, financial regulations for campaigns, and the impact of information and communication technologies (ICTs) on electoral processes. The second day of AESF IV focused largely on topics specific to elections in Asian countries and featured discussions on contemporary challenges in Asian elections, civic education, and the protection of vulnerable populations.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Global" /><category term="Acuerdo de Lima" /><category term="EPDE" /><category term="ANDE" /><category term="ANFREL" /><category term="E-HORN" /><category term="Misión de Observación Electoral" /><category term="ENEMO" /><category term="CeMI" /><category term="LADE" /><category term="KHRC" /><summary type="html">From August 25 to 26, 2018, the GNDEM Coordinating Committee, representing the nine regional networks, met in Colombo, Sri Lanka for the Sixth Implementation Meeting of the Declaration of Global Principles for Nonpartisan Election Observation. The Coordinating Committee discussed recent challenges and opportunities in citizen election observation, and further clarified and refined network priorities and standard operating procedures, including the approval of the first set of GNDEM Protocols.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/v1542647904/gndem/GNDEM%20in%20Colombo%202.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">GNDEM Members Convene for Academy on Open Data Analysis and Disinformation Monitoring</title><link href="https://gndem.org/es/stories/gndem-members-convene-for-academy-on-open-data-analysis-and-disinformation-monitoring/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="GNDEM Members Convene for Academy on Open Data Analysis and Disinformation Monitoring" /><published>2018-05-14T04:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-05-14T04:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-convene-for-academy-on-open-data-analysis-and-disinformation-monitoring</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gndem.org/stories/gndem-members-convene-for-academy-on-open-data-analysis-and-disinformation-monitoring/">&lt;p&gt;From April 24-27, 2018, 15 citizen election observer groups from 11 countries, including 10 GNDEM members, convened in Belgrade, Serbia for an academy on information and electoral integrity through open election data analysis and monitoring the spread, prevalence and scope of disinformation during elections. The four-day academy included discussions on methodologies for monitoring disinformation in traditional and social media, methods for using open election data as part of election observation efforts, and various tools and skills for opening and analyzing election data to enhance fact-based findings. GNDEM members identified these issues as highly important to electoral integrity following a similar academy in 2017, and the peer-to-peer learning opportunity allowed members to share recent innovative approaches and learn from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GNDEM members who participated in the academy are: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zgjedhje.al/faqe.php?id=1&amp;amp;l2=115&amp;amp;l3=46&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Society for Democratic Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Albania), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/kriik.al/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KRIIK Albania Association&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kzln.org.al/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coalition for Free and Fair Elections&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Albania), &lt;a href=&quot;http://most.org.mk/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Citizens Association MOST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Macedonia), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cemi.org.me/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Center CEMI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Montenegro), &lt;a href=&quot;http://podlupom.org/v2/en&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pod Lupom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Bosnia and Herzegovina), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://crta.rs/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;(Serbia), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cesid.rs/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Center for Free Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Serbia), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://isfed.ge/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Society For Fair Elections and Democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Georgia), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oporaua.org/en&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Civil Network OPORA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Ukraine), &lt;a href=&quot;https://promolex.md/?lang=ro&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Promo-LEX Association&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Moldova), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://coalition.kg/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coalition for Democracy and Civil Society&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Kyrgyzstan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The academy began by taking stock of disinformation in elections, including what tactics are being used, how it manifests in traditional and online media, and how it impacts the integrity of electoral processes. Participants highlighted challenges they have encountered in monitoring, mitigating or combatting disinformation. The Center for Research, Transparency and Accountability (CRTA) in Serbia highlighted their efforts at media monitoring and fact-checking around the country’s most recent elections, and how they formulated messages aimed at countering false or misleading information. The International Society For Fair Elections and Democracy (ISFED) in Georgia discussed how they were structuring and designing their methodology to monitor social media ahead of the presidential election this October, using new tools developed to monitor and analyze the large amount of data associated with social media postings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The academy also focused on the use of open election data, and how advocating for and using official data can be a powerful tool to counter disinformation and misleading content. Transparent and accessible data can help election management bodies combat rumors while increasing citizen observers’ ability to fact-check information. Participants learned about tools that can be used to convert data from into open formats or that can be used to extract large data sets, and were able to practice using such tools to analyze real examples of datasets that would benefit and enhance their observation efforts. Drawing on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openelectiondata.net/en/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Election Data Initiative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;’s Election Data Academy, participating citizen observers learned new techniques and tools for analyzing common election data, such as polling station lists (you can test you knowledge of data analysis by going through the modules &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/en/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;here&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;; also available in &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/es/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spanish&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/fr/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;French&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/my/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Burmese&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://openelectiondata.net/ar/academy/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arabic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the conclusion of the academy, each participant identified specific points of action that they will take back to their observer groups to enhance their respective election monitoring efforts. As new challenges and tactics are used by those seeking to undermine the credibility of electoral processes, GNDEM members must work to adapt new methodologies and incorporate new tools into their monitoring efforts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Central &amp; Eastern Europe" /><category term="Eurasia" /><summary type="html">From April 24-27, 2018, 15 citizen election observer groups from 11 countries, including 10 GNDEM members, convened in Belgrade, Serbia for an academy on information and electoral integrity through open election data analysis and monitoring the spread, prevalence and scope of disinformation during elections. The four-day academy included discussions on methodologies for monitoring disinformation in traditional and social media, methods for using open election data as part of election observation efforts, and various tools and skills for opening and analyzing election data to enhance fact-based findings. GNDEM members identified these issues as highly important to electoral integrity following a similar academy in 2017, and the peer-to-peer learning opportunity allowed members to share recent innovative approaches and learn from one another.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://res.cloudinary.com/gndem/image/upload/v1541355317/gndem/gndem-members-convene-for-academy-1.jpg" /></entry></feed>